National Archives and Records Service Copies of Federal Documentation on Black Workers 5584
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- U.S. Department of Labor. Lawrence A. Oxley. Subject Files. (Box 10)
  - Interior, Department of - Office of Education -, 1933-1934 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Documents concerning an educational program designed as emergency relief projects for Blacks. News Release, "South Faces Difficult Problem Financing Schools, Committee finds," May 11, 1934- (Findings of the committee on financial support of the National Conference on the Education of Blacks. Includes statistics on the funding of public schools population, per capita income, teachers salaries, per student spending, comparative analysis of Black and white schools and their students and between the south and the rest of the United States); information on the Public Works Administration and federal emergency relief projects available to Black public schools. Projects include construction, vocational training, vocational rehabilitation, adult education and preschool education
  - Interior, Department of - Office of Education - Survey Opportunities for Vocational education and Guidance for Blacks -, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Correspondence concerning the Technical Advisory Committee for the National Survey of Opportunities for Vocational Education and Vocational Guidance of Blacks. Black job applicants requests aid to secure employment in this project.
  - Interstate Commerce Commission, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Correspondence re the formulation of rules for protection of Blacks using buses and trucks
  - Labor Department - Bureau of Labor Statistics, Luncheon Club, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Routine announcements
  - Labor Department - Children's Bureau -, 1922-1934 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Information on child labor, migrants, welfare and social security, services relating to youths, both Black and white; re Black delinquent youth not properly placed in correctional institution due to lack of space and racial segregation. Includes statistics on population,, delinquents and types of crimes committee by Black youth; Bibliography of publications by the Children's Bureau about working mothers and youth with specific information on Blacks.
  - Labor Department - Conciliation Service -, 1932-1939 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    Correspondence alleging discrimination against Blacks in employment by private sector employers and labor unions in Chicago, Illinois and Indiana. Discrimination by International Longshoremen's Association in Texas. Alleged discrimination against Blacks on Works Progress Administration projects and Public Works Administration projects; Memorandum listing Black political, educational, and social leaders to be invited to the ceremony dedicating the new Labor Department Building.
  - Labor Department - Conciliation Service - Joint Conference Committee of the Community Progressive Black Painters Union -, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Documents re a New York Black painters labor union allege discrimination against Blacks in private sector employment and federal emergency relief programs. Recommendation from Lawrence Oxley for the Labor Department to cease relations with the Committee.
- U.S. Department of Labor. Lawrence A. Oxley. Subject Files. (Box 11)
  - Labor Department - Division of Labor Standards - Apprenticeship Training, Federal Committee on -, 1934-1939 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Includes statistics on Black unemployment and students in secondary schools of ten states receiving grand-in-aid including Alabama, Delaware, Florida, Louisiana, Massachusetts, Missouri, North Carolina, South Carolina, Texas, Wyoming.
  - Labor Department - Fitzgerald, Henry J. -, 1934-1937 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Routine internal administrative correspondence
  - Labor Department - Gompers S.J. -, 1934-1936 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Includes statistics on salaries and staffing of Blacks in the Labor Department, United States Employment Service and the National Reemployment Service. Data from the Washington, DC Employment Service on job applicants and employee placements divided by race.
  - Labor Department - Hinrichs, A.F. -, 1930-1935 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Correspondence regarding the Labor Department's public policy concerning state conferences on Black employment problems; Memorandum to Lawrence A. Oxley, April 15, 1935, requesting a study of the decline in Black labor union membership during the depression. Author suggests the reason involves unemployment; Memorandum to A.F. Hinrichs, March 4, 1935, re National and International labor unions in the Construction Industry, affiliated and unaffiliated with the AFL in which discrimination against Blacks is traditional or provided for in the union constitution; Memorandum to A.F. Hinrichs, January 30, 1935, noting theories on depressed wages in the south for both Black and white employees, including bibliography; Conference notes re detailed position description of Lawrence Oxley's position of Chief, Division of Black Labor in the Labor Department; Memorandum to A.F. Hinrichs, October 3, 1934 listing Black government officials and national organizations concerned with educational, economic, professional, political and general advancement of Blacks. Suggested bibliography on the Black in industry; Memorandum to A.F. Hinrichs re statistics on the distribution of Black miners by counties in West Virginia, in 1930
  - Labor Department - Immigration Service -, 1932-1936 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Correspondence and petitions from Blacks alleging racial discrimination and requesting to be sent to Africa
  - Labor Department - Lubin, Isador -, 1934-1939 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Correspondence re procedure on arranging state conferences concerning Black employment problems. Requests for travel authorization to conferences concerning Blacks where the Labor Department's presence might have positive political influence for the Franklin D. Roosevelt administration.
  - Labor Department - Lubin, Isador - Weekly Progress Reports -, 1935-1937 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Detailed accounts of Lawrence Oxley's action as Chief, Division of Black Labor.
  - Labor Department - Perkins, Frances M. -, 1934-1937 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Correspondence and pamphlets, including general facilitative office correspondence to Perkins, Oxley, and other officials in the Labor Department. Contains routine solicitation for information on Black employment and general information on Secretary of Labor and the Labor Department.
  - Labor Department - Perkins, Frances M. -, 1934-1936 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Correspondence, reports and pamphlets. Includes correspondence to Perkins and Oxley on discrimination against Blacks in employment. Statistics on Black workers and Black education. Reports to Perkins on the Division of Black Labor and speeches. Exchange on alleged discrimination against Blacks in Labor Department. Includes hostile correspondence from Black person relating to Black federal employees; Letter from General Counsel of International Association of Railroad Employees on discrimination against Blacks in the railroad industry and problems with railroad craft unions and their exclusive jurisdiction under the Railway Labor Act, August 1, 1936; Memorandum containing rationale for maintenance of staff o the Division of Black Labor rather than a reduction in force of the office, noting that an active Division may have political influence in the voting patterns of the south, June 1, 1936; Memorandum recommending that the Democratic National Committee be assigned the task of compiling information about the New Deal Administration and its impact on Black employment and emergency relief. Goal is to produce a publication with information favorable to Blacks to influence the voting pattern of the south, March 23, 1936; Memorandum-report concerning the first meeting of the National Negro Congress, February 14, 1936 in Chicago. Notes John P. Davis as founder of the organization. Describes organization's leaders as communists, March 5 1936; Memorandum-progress report on Blacks and the New Deal. Discusses problems on barriers to entry in employment, job searching, and employment opportunities. Provides an economic analysis of the Black population. Discusses discrimination against Blacks in emergency relief programs by the NRA, the Public Works Administration, the Tennessee Valley Authority, the Civilian Conservation Corps, and related trade unions. Lists achievements of the Division of Black unions. Lists achievements of the Division of Black Labor, November 9, 1935; Letter describing activities of Georgia Teachers and Educational Association, a Black teachers' association. Includes a recommendation to hire a Black supervisor to the Georgia Relief Emergency Administration. Statistics from 1933-34 on the number of schools, comparative analysis on Black and white teachers and Black and white school enrollment. Goals for improving elementary and secondary education for Blacks in Georgia, July 19, 1935; Memorandum giving opinion on Title VII of proposed Economic Security Act. Discusses grant in aid for vocational education. Proposal of statement to be included in the Economic Security Act providing equal opportunity of appropriations for grant in aid to Black and white schools. Reviews the Second Morrill Act and the Smith-Lever Act of 1914. Statistical table on discrimination, January 23, 1935; Memorandum discussing circulating rumors that Labor Department will dismiss Black blue collar workers in favor of whites. Calls for continued employment, the creation of additional employment opportunities and the end of discrimination for Blacks, December 14, 1934; Memorandum from Lawrence Oxley quoting the 1934 American Federation of Labor (AFL) resolution against discrimination of Blacks, October 22, 1934; Memorandum discusses the staffing of Black blue collar workers in the Labor Department. Insofar as possible, discrimination against Blacks will be avoided, January 2, 1934; "The Division of Negro Labor, Department of Labor," describes activities of the Division of Black Labor.
  - Labor Department - Phillips, Karl F., 1934-1939 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Includes routine internal administrative correspondence
- U.S. Department of Labor. Lawrence A. Oxley. Subject Files. (Box 12)
  - Labor Department - U.S. Employment Service - Black White-Collar Employment Survey -, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Documents soliciting various state employment services for eligible Black job applicants to work on a Works Progress Administration project. Surveying Black white-collar employees.
  - Labor Department - U.S. Employment Service - Special Reports - Arthur, George R. -, 1933-1940 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Reports on the relationship between the state employment services and Black job applicants in Dallas, Texas; Memphis, Tennessee; Birmingham and Montgomery, Alabama; Los Angeles and San Francisco, California; Kansas City, Missouri; and Denver, Colorado. Alleged discrimination against Blacks in these areas. Analysis of occupation and characteristics of emergency relief recipients for Chicago, Illinois.
  - Labor Department -Wage and Hour Division -, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Documents re Black job applicants requesting aid in securing employment at the Wage and Hour Division of the Labor Department.
  - Miscellaneous Complaints, 1928-1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Letters from Blacks complaining of discrimination in staffing and employment from various parts of the country.
  - National Archives -, 1934-1937 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Correspondence re Lawrence Oxley's attempts at ensuring employment Black job applicants in the newly created National Archives
  - National Recovery Administration, 1934-1935 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    Reports and correspondence concerning NRA fair competition industry codes and Lawrence Oxley's participation on the Labor Advisory Board ensuring against racial discrimination; "A Wage Differential Based on Race," re discrimination against Blacks in wages and NRA fair competition industry codes; "Report on Effect of NRA Codes on Blacks, March 21, 1934," re alleged discrimination against Black workers. Describes the application of NRA fair competition codes to southern industries and the resulting effects on Blacks; "The Black and Wage Differentials Under the Codes," describes regional and population wage differentials under the NRA codes with respect to Blacks.
  - National Recovery Administration - Fair Competition Industry Codes - Central Weaving and Spinning Company -, 1934-1938 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    Appeal for exemption from the NRA Act fair competition industry codes for the textile industry by the Central Weaving and Spinning Company of Fayetteville, North Carolina. Discrimination is apparent as the company contends, Blacks are inferior employees. Includes newspaper articles, statistics on Black births and deaths from 1933-1936 in the United States.
  - National Recovery Administration - Fair Competition Industry Codes - Mente and Company -, 1933-1935 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Appeal for exemption from the NRA Act fair competition industry code for the textile industry by the Mente Company of New Orleans, Louisiana and the Selma Manufacturing Company of Selma, Alabama. Discrimination is apparent as the companies contend that Blacks are inferior employees and have a low productivity rate. Statistics on Black property ownership, economic, educational and religious progress in North Carolina, Virginia, and Georgia.
  - National Recovery Administration - Fair Competition Industry Codes - Nachman, D. and Company -, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    Appeal for exemption from the NRA fair competition industry code for the textile industry by the D. Nachman and Company of Augusta, Georgia. Racial discrimination is apparent as the company contends Black women are inferior employees and have a low productivity rate.
- U.S. Department of Labor. Lawrence A. Oxley. Subject Files. (Box 13)
  - National Recovery Administration - Fair Competition Industry Codes - Southland Manufacturing Company, 1934-1935 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Appeal for exemption from the NRA Fair Competition Code for the clothing industry by the Southland Manufacturing Company of Montgomery, Alabama. Discrimination against Blacks is alleged. The company contends Blacks are inferior employees and have a low productivity rate.
  - National Recovery, Joint Committee on -, 1934-1936 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    "Two Years with the Joint Committee on National Recovery, 1933-35." A publicity pamphlet which states goals and accomplishments of the Committee and includes their progress on behalf of Blacks in the New Deal. Information on Black industrial workers, farm hands and farmers, dayworkers, emergency relief recipients and the Tennessee Valley Authority. States relationship between the federal government and the Committee; correspondence, memorandums, meeting minutes concerning the progress of Blacks under the New Deal including the National Youth Administration, Civilian Conservation Corps, Works Project Administration, Public Works Administration and Resettlement Administration. Protest against discrimination against Blacks within these administrations and in the AFL trade unions. Discussion of the fair competition industry codes of the NRA, specifically including the cotton, laundry, tobacco and mining industries. Information and statistics on the conditions Black day workers encounter; Memorandum to all member organizations of the Joint Committee February 23, 1935 discusses the discriminatory effects against Blacks by the implementation of the Farm Tenant Homes Act of 1935. Provisions render discrimination against Black tenant farmers, sharecroppers and marginal land owners; Memorandum to Isador Lubin, October 24, 1934, re observations of an annual dinner for the Joint Committee. Presents administrative viewpoints on how Black unemployment problems are viewed and solved.
  - National Recovery, Joint Committee on -, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    "Occupational Status of the Blacks in the Iron and Steel Industry: Pittsburgh and Environs, May 23, 1934," by Wilson F. Alden, Pittsburgh Urban League. History and current information including alleged discrimination against Blacks in the Iron and Steel Industry from Alleghany County, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Statistics on Black employees and their occupations; "An Analysis of the Occupational Opportunities for Blacks in Allegheny County," by Howard D. Gould. Report on the problems of Black employment and resulting job opportunities in Allegheny County, Pennsylvania. Statistics on population (1910-1930), migration, employment, occupations, industries employing Blacks and wages.
  - Publications -, 1933-1941 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Published reports on racial employment trends in national defense, black employment opportunities in Kentucky, employment security and the Blacks, Black youth, placement of Black workers by the United States Employment Service, earnings and hours of Black workers in independent tobacco industry, memorandums and executive orders from President Roosevelt condemning discrimination in defense industries. Report on the situation of Black women workers.
  - Public Works Administration - Agreements -, 1935-1936 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Agreements between Public Works Administration and the Labor Department which guaranteed employment to Blacks on a percentage basis for individual PWA projects. Projects are located in New Jersey, New York, Alabama, Ohio, Illinois, Tennessee, Kentucky and Indiana.
  - Public Works Administration - Contracts - Isador Lubin -, 1934-1936 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Alleged discrimination against Blacks on PWA projects in New York City, Kansas City, Saint Louis, Los Angeles, Fort Wayne, Georgetown, Greensville, Point Pleasant, Mantina, and Florida. Suggested clauses to be inserted in project agreements to safeguard Blacks against discrimination.
  - Public Works Administration - Housing Contracts -, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Suggested clauses to be inserted into PWA contracts. Chicago, Cleveland, housing project agreements to prevent discrimination against Black workers. Alleged discrimination against Blacks on these projects in Chicago. List of building and construction trade labor unions barring Black membership. Racial statistics on emergency relief recipient and population in the United States and occupations in the building and construction trade held by Blacks in Chicago.
  - Resettlement Administration, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    RE alleged discrimination against Blacks in employment on a project in North Carolina. Information on the number and occupations of Black employees in the Resettlement Administration.
  - Tennessee Valley Authority -, 1934-1938 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    Statistics on wages paid to Black workers with the TVA. Request of Lawrence Oxley to visit the work sites to prevent discrimination against Blacks in staffing.
- U.S. Department of Labor. Lawrence A. Oxley. Subject Files. (Box 14)
  - Tennessee Valley Authority - Discrimination, 1935-1937 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Alleged discrimination against Blacks in staffing and employment with the Tennessee Valley Authority.
  - Tobacco -, 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Alleged discrimination against Blacks in staffing at a tobacco plant in Ohio; "The Tobacco Industry in North Carolina," report on the tobacco industry with statistics for major companies on profits, production, employees, wages, hours. Discrimination against Blacks is charged because of the low wage rates prescribed by the NRA in the fair competition industry code.
  - Tobacco Study -, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Bibliography on the tobacco industry. Questionnaire schedule used for Black and white employees of the tobacco industry.
  - Transportation, Federal Coordinator of -, 1934-1936 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Alleged discrimination against Black railroad workers by American Federation of Labor railroad unions, resulting in unemployment.
  - Unemployment Census -, 1937-1938 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Statistics on unemployment divided by race for Arizona, Delaware, and New Hampshire
  - Works Progress Administration - Available Housing for Research Project -, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Requests for office space from Black contacts for a WPA study concerning Black white-collar employees.
  - Works Progress Administration - Miscellaneous Correspondence -, 1935-1938 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Alleged discrimination against Blacks in staffing at the WPA in North Carolina, South Carolina, Los Angeles, California, and Texas. Job applicants requesting aid in securing employment in the WPA.
  - Works Progress Administration - Black Press Digest -, 1937-1938 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    Weekly report on the articles found in Black newspapers concerning the Works Progress Administration.
  - Works Progress Administration - Savannah, Georgia -, 1934-1936 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Alleged discrimination against Blacks in staffing and employment with the Works Progress Administration projects at Savannah, Georgia.
  - Works Progress Administration - Alfred E. Smith -, 1934-1938 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    Alleged discrimination against Blacks in staffing and employment with the WPA in Alabama, Ohio, South Carolina, Nebraska, Louisiana, Georgia, Mississippi, Texas, Virginia, Maryland, North Carolina, Illinois, Massachusetts, Kansas, Missouri, and Florida. Job applicants request aid in securing employment with this administration.
  - Works Progress Administration - Workers' Education -, 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    Bulletins from the Workers' Education Training Center, Livingstone College, Salisbury, North Carolina funded by the WPA. Bulletin on workers' education from the Federal Emergency Relief Administration.
- U.S. Department of Labor. Lawrence A. Oxley. State Employment Service State Files. (Box 15)
  - Alabama - Complaints -, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Letters alleging discriminations against Blacks by Birmingham, Alabama, State Employment Service Office. Complaint that the office is disregarding the civil service eligible lists for Black job applicants.
  - Alabama - General Correspondence -, 1936-1938 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Concerning a conference to be held with the Alabama State Employment Service on the problems of Black employment and racial discrimination.
  - Alabama - Survey, 1934-1938 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Report on the relationship between the Alabama State Employment Service and Black job applicants. Statistics on population, 1910-1933, emergency relief recipients, occupations, local industry, and data on job applicants and employee placement divided by race in Birmingham and Alabama. Report of conference held with service concerning Black employment and racial discrimination. Proposal for urban renewal in Birmingham. 1934,1938.
  - Arizona - General Correspondence -, 1938-1939 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    Newspaper article and correspondence re the opening of a Black employment service. Alleged discrimination against Blacks by Arizona State Employment Service.
  - Arkansas - General Correspondence -, 1938-1939 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    Alleged discrimination against Blacks by Arkansas State Employment Service concerning civil service merit examinations and eligible lists in Little Rock.
  - Arkansas - Survey, 1936 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    Report on the relationship between the Arkansas State Employment Service and Black job applicants, Statistics on population, 1910-1933, emergency relief recipients, occupations, local industry and data on job applicants and employee placements divided by race for Little Rock and Arkansas. Examines cotton industry, tenant farming, housing and slave labor in Arkansas.
  - California - Complaints -, 1938-1939 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    Alleged discriminations against Blacks in staffing by the Civilian Conservation Corps, Shasta Dam Project, Shasta County, Tulare California.